<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: libgit2 | Ben Straub]]></title>
  <link href="http://ben.github.com/blog/categories/libgit2/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ben.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-01T20:41:17-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://ben.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ben Straub]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[libgit2: Walking History]]></title>
    <link href="http://ben.github.com/2013/10/02/revwalk/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-02T12:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ben.github.com/2013/10/02/revwalk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Making new commits and dealing with the working directory is only half of what git is for.
Most of the data in a git repository is historical; old commits, old versions of files.
Let's take a look at how you can use libgit2 to handle that information.</p>

<h2>Commits</h2>

<p>It's pretty easy to just load up a commit and start poking around with the data inside it.
It seems pretty logical to do this when you want to walk the commit history of the project, right?
Let's take a look at how that turns out:</p>

<p>```c
  void visit(git_commit *c)
  {</p>

<pre><code>ize_t i, num_parents = git_commit_parentcount(c);

/* Print some stuff about this commit */
char oidstr[10] = {0};
git_oid_tostr(oidstr, 9, git_commit_id(c));
printf("%s\n%s\n\n", oidstr,
       commit_message(c));

for (i=0; i&lt;num_parents; i++) {
  /* Do the same for the parents */
  git_commit *p;
  if (!git_commit_parent(&amp;p, c, i))
    visit(p);
  git_commit_free(p);
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  git_commit <em>commit;
  /</em> elided: dereference HEAD to a commit */
  visit(commit);
```</p>

<p>But what if you want something other than a depth-first traversal?
Maybe you want to sort the results by commit time?
That's a pretty tricky bit of code to write.
What if your repo has a non-trivial amount of history?
You'll run out of stack frames pretty quickly.</p>

<p>There's an API for that.</p>

<h2>Revwalk</h2>

<p>The revwalk API works similarly to what we just wrote above, with a few exceptions:</p>

<ul>
<li>It has a configurable sort order for the output.</li>
<li>It's not built on recursion, so even very large repos can be walked efficiently.</li>
<li>You get to choose your start and end points.</li>
<li>It offers some history simplification.</li>
</ul>


<p>Let's walk through this one step at a time.
First, you have to create a walker object:</p>

<p><code>c
  git_revwalk *walk;
  if (git_revwalk_new(&amp;walk, repo) &lt; 0)
  { /* ERROR */ }
</code></p>

<p>Pretty straightforward, not much to explain here.
Next, let's configure the walk:</p>

<p>```c
  git_revwalk_sorting(walk,</p>

<pre><code>GIT_SORT_TOPOLOGICAL |
GIT_SORT_TIME)
</code></pre>

<p>  git_revwalk_push_head(walk);
  git_revwalk_hide_glob(walk, "tags/*");</p>

<p>  git_object *obj;
  git_revparse_single(&amp;obj, repo, "HEAD~10");
  git_revwalk_hide(walk, git_object_id(obj));
  git_object_free(obj);
```</p>

<p>We're doing several things here:</p>

<ol>
<li>We set the sort order to "topological + time".
This sounds a bit arcane, but it's just what you'd want for a log viewer: parents after children, sorted by commit time.</li>
<li>We "push" the HEAD commit onto the walk.
This tells the walk that the HEAD and its ancestors should be visited when we start iterating.
You can even do more than one "push" (i.e. all of the known refs, for behavior like <code>git log --all</code>).</li>
<li>We "hide" from the walk all commits that are included in a tag.
The pattern will match all the refs under "refs/tags", dereference them to commits, and exclude those commits and their ancestors from the walk.</li>
<li>We also hide all commits that precede the 10th ancestor of HEAD.
This has much the same effect as passing <code>-10</code> to <code>git log</code>.</li>
</ol>


<p>Obviously, these particular choices won't be right for every application, but there are more than enough options to (hopefully) fit your use case.
And if not, you can always fall back to writing your own walk using the commit API.</p>

<p>Now we're ready to run the walk, and print out some facts about each commit:</p>

<p>```c
  git_oid oid;
  while (git_revwalk_next(&amp;oid, walk) == 0) {</p>

<pre><code>git_commit *c;
char oidstr[10] = {0};

git_commit_lookup(&amp;c, repo, &amp;oid);
git_oid_tostr(oidstr, 9, &amp;oid);
printf("%s\n%s\n\n", oidstr,
       git_commit_message(c));

git_commit_free(c);
</code></pre>

<p>  }
```</p>

<p><em>[Implementing <code>--graph</code> is left as an exercise for the reader.]</em></p>

<p>That wasn't so bad, was it?
Traveling through time was never so easy.
All that's left is to clean up the mess we've made.</p>

<p><code>c
  git_repository_free(repo);
</code></p>

<p>## What now?

I dunno.
What are you trying to do?
You could always check out my [other libgit2 posts](/blog/categories/libgit2/) for some ideas.
Or look for help [everywhere else](https://www.google.com/search?q=how%20do%20I%20use%20libgit2%20to).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[libgit2: Refs, Tags, and Branching]]></title>
    <link href="http://ben.github.com/2013/06/03/refs-tags-and-branching/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-03T16:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ben.github.com/2013/06/03/refs-tags-and-branching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Refs are a powerful way of annotating a git repository's history.
Libgit2, of course, provides several ways of working with them.</p>

<h2>Refs</h2>

<p>There are several ways to get a handle on a ref in libgit2.
If you just want one:</p>

<p><code>c
git_reference *ref;
git_reference_lookup(&amp;ref, repo, "refs/heads/master");
</code></p>

<p>The string argument has to be the full name of the ref; just <code>master</code> won't do.
There's also a shortcut to use a more humane ref name:</p>

<p><code>c
git_reference_dwim(&amp;ref, repo, "master");
</code></p>

<p>That one applies the <a href="http://git-scm.com/docs/git-rev-parse.html#_specifying_revisions">standard git precedence rules</a> to figure out which ref you mean.</p>

<p>There's also a way of getting to <em>all</em> of the refs in a repository:</p>

<p>```c
int each_ref(git_reference <em>ref, void </em>payload)
{
  printf("  %s\n", git_reference_name(ref));
  return 0;
}</p>

<p>git_reference_foreach(repo, each_ref, NULL);
```</p>

<p>Once you have a <code>git_reference*</code>, what can you do with it? Well, you can check to see if it's symbolic (like <code>HEAD</code> usually is) or direct (like <code>master</code> usually is):</p>

<p>```c
switch(git_reference_type(ref)) {
  case GIT_REF_OID:
  {</p>

<pre><code>char oidstr[41] = {0};
git_oid_fmt(oidstr, git_reference_target(ref));
printf("It's a direct reference to %s\n", oidstr);
break;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  case GIT_REF_SYMBOLIC:
  {</p>

<pre><code>printf("It's a symbolic reference to '%s'\n",
  git_reference_symbolic_target(ref));
break;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>You can change its target, which <a href="/2013/04/02/libgit2-checkout/">in combination with <code>git_checkout_head</code></a> would get close to the branch-switching behavior of <code>git checkout</code>:</p>

<p>```c
git_reference *new_ref;
git_reference_symbolic_set_target(&amp;new_ref, ref,</p>

<pre><code>                              "refs/heads/devel");
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Note that a <code>git_reference</code> is conceptually immutable, so changing the target of one gives you a new instance rather than modifying the one you already have.</p>

<p>You can also create new references. This is a good start towards <code>git checkout -b</code>:</p>

<p>```c
git_object *obj;
git_revparse_single(&amp;obj, repo, "master");
git_reference_create(&amp;new_ref, repo, "refs/heads/feature1",</p>

<pre><code>                 git_object_id(obj), 1);
</code></pre>

<p>git_object_free(obj);
```</p>

<h2>Tags</h2>

<p>Git tags come in two flavors: <a href="http://git-scm.com/book/en/Git-Basics-Tagging">lightweight and annotated</a>.
Lightweight tags are just regular references, so you can handle them with the refs API.
But annotated tags have structured data stored in the object database.
This is represented in libgit2 as a <code>git_tag</code> structure.</p>

<p>Again, there are several ways to get your hands on a tag annotation.
You can do a direct lookup if you know the hash of the annotation:</p>

<p><code>c
git_oid oid;
git_oid_fromstr(&amp;oid,
  "bbea158ddb36042aa47ce1e4d0188684b20157d3");
git_tag *tag;
git_tag_lookup(&amp;tag, repo, &amp;oid);
</code></p>

<p>If all you know is the tag's name, it takes a couple of steps:</p>

<p><code>c
git_reference *ref;
git_reference_lookup(&amp;ref, repo, "refs/tags/annotated");
git_tag *tag;
git_reference_peel((git_object**)&amp;tag, ref, GIT_OBJ_TAG);
</code></p>

<p>What can you do with one of these guys?
Mostly they're for inspecting properties:</p>

<p><code>c
// Get the full name of the tag
const char *name = git_tag_name(tag);
// Get the tag's message
const char *msg = git_tag_message(tag);
// Get the targeted object's ID
git_oid *target = git_tag_target_id(tag);
// Get information about the tagger
git_signature *sig = git_tag_signature(tag);
</code></p>

<p>How do you create tags?
As I mentioned above, lightweight tags are just references, so you'd use <code>git_reference_create</code>, and give it a name like <code>refs/tags/foo</code>.
Annotated tags have their own creation call:</p>

<p>```c
  git_signature *sig;
  git_signature_now(&amp;sig, "Mr. Tagger", "mr@tagger.com");
  git_oid annotation_id;
  git_tag_create(</p>

<pre><code>&amp;annotation_id,      // newly-created object's id
repo,                // repository
"new_annotated_tag", // tag name
obj,                 // tag target
sig,                 // signature
"A message",         // message
1);                  // force if name collides
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>It turns out an annotated tag is just a lightweight tag (regular ref) that points to a tag annotation object, which in turn points to something else.
So you can create an annotation with <code>git_tag_annotation_create</code>, then create the tag ref separately.</p>

<p>Don't forget this is C; always free your newly-created heap objects with <code>git_*_free</code> calls.
In this case:</p>

<p><code>c
git_signature_free(sig);
git_object_free(obj);
git_tag_free(tag);
git_reference_free(ref);
</code></p>

<p>The rule of thumb here is if you declared it as a pointer, it probably needs freeing.</p>

<p>## What now?

I dunno.
What are you trying to do?
You could always check out my [other libgit2 posts](/blog/categories/libgit2/) for some ideas.
Or look for help [everywhere else](https://www.google.com/search?q=how%20do%20I%20use%20libgit2%20to).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[libgit2: Checkout]]></title>
    <link href="http://ben.github.com/2013/04/02/libgit2-checkout/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-02T10:43:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ben.github.com/2013/04/02/libgit2-checkout</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So you've got this <a href="/2013/03/05/libgit2-the-repository">git repository</a>, and it's got a bunch of stuff in it -- refs, trees, blobs, commits -- and you want to work with that stuff.
One way to think about that stuff is by thinking about how it's organized into <a href="http://git-scm.com/2011/07/11/reset.html">three trees</a>, and moving stuff between those trees.
In libgit2, the way you get stuff from a commit into the index and the working tree is by using the checkout API.</p>

<h2>This isn't "<code>git checkout</code>"</h2>

<p>The first thing to realize is that libgit2 isn't just a reimplementation of the git command line tool.
That means that some terminology is reused, but doesn't necessarily work the same way.
In libgit2, checkout is all about modifying the index and/or working directory, based on content from the index or a tree in the object database.</p>

<p>Libgit2's checkout API has (as of this writing) three modes:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>git_checkout_head</code> updates the index and working tree to match the content of the tree pointed to by <code>HEAD</code>.</li>
<li><code>git_checkout_index</code> updates the working directory to match the content of the index.</li>
<li><code>git_checkout_tree</code> updates the working directory to the content of a specified tree.</li>
</ul>


<p>None of those deal with actually moving <code>HEAD</code> around, which is most of what I use <code>git checkout</code> for, but hey.
If you want to move refs around, try the refs API.</p>

<h2>Wholesale</h2>

<p>The general form for calling a checkout API is this:</p>

<p><code>c
git_repository *repo;
git_checkout_opts opts = GIT_CHECKOUT_OPTS_INIT;
// customize options...
int error = git_checkout_head(repo, &amp;opts);
</code></p>

<p>That <code>opts</code> structure is where all the good stuff happens.
The default mode of operation is to</p>

<ol>
<li>Check every file in the tree that's being read for differences with the index and/or working directory, and</li>
<li>do absolutely nothing to the working directory.</li>
</ol>


<p>By design, you have to be very explicit when you're writing stuff to the working directory.
To specify what strategy you want the checkout to use, you modify <code>opts.checkout_strategy</code>, usually to one of these values:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>GIT_CHECKOUT_SAFE</code> will update files that match what's in the index (files that haven't been changed), but won't create missing files.</li>
<li><code>GIT_CHECKOUT_SAFE_CREATE</code> does the above plus creating missing files. This is what <a href="/2013/02/01/stupid-libgit2-tricks-cloning"><code>git_clone</code></a> uses by default.</li>
<li><code>GIT_CHECKOUT_FORCE</code> does the above, plus overwriting uncommitted changes.
This is the most like <code>git checkout -f</code>.</li>
</ul>


<p>There are some other behavior flags you can include in this field as well:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>GIT_CHECKOUT_ALLOW_CONFLICTS</code> allows the checkout to proceed even if there are unresolved merge conflicts (the default is to return an error if any are present).</li>
<li><code>GIT_CHECKOUT_REMOVE_UNTRACKED</code> removes files that aren't being tracked by git (but doesn't touch ignored files).</li>
<li><code>GIT_CHECKOUT_REMOVE_IGNORED</code> removes ignored files that aren't in the index (but doesn't touch non-ignored files that are untracked).</li>
</ul>


<p>That's just a sampling; the <a href="https://github.com/libgit2/libgit2/blob/HEAD/include/git2/checkout.h#files">header comments</a>, are pretty helpful for using the rest.</p>

<h2>Progress and notification callbacks</h2>

<p>The <code>git_checkout_*</code> calls are blocking.
If you want to know how things are going, or display progress to the user, you have to register callbacks.
There are two types.</p>

<h3>Progress</h3>

<p>The progress callback notifies you as checkout actually writes files to the working directory.
Here's how one might look:</p>

<p>```c
static void checkout_progress(
  const char <em>path,
  size_t current,
  size_t total,
  void </em>payload)
{
  printf("checkout: %3d%% - %s\n",</p>

<pre><code>100*current/total,
path);
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>// ...
git_checkout_opts opts = GIT_CHECKOUT_OPTS_INIT;
opts.progress_cb = checkout_progress;
int error = git_checkout_head(repo, &amp;opts);
```</p>

<p>The output looks something like this:</p>

<p><code>text
checkout:   0% - (null)
checkout:  12% - a/a1
checkout:  25% - a/a1.txt
checkout:  37% - a/a2.txt
checkout:  50% - b/b1.txt
checkout:  62% - b/b2.txt
checkout:  75% - c/c1.txt
checkout:  87% - c/c2.txt
checkout: 100% - master.txt
</code></p>

<h3>"Notifications"</h3>

<p>The other callback you can specify is more specific about what's going on with the files in the working directory.
Checkout actually uses diff to do its work, so it doesn't always overwrite every file in the working directory.
If the contents match, no work is done at all.
That little bit of understanding might make it easier to see this callback in action:</p>

<p>```c
static int checkout_notify_cb(
  git_checkout_notify_t why,
  const char <em>path,
  const git_diff_file </em>baseline,
  const git_diff_file <em>target,
  const git_diff_file </em>workdir,
  void *payload)
{
  printf("path '%s' - ", path);
  switch (why) {
  case GIT_CHECKOUT_NOTIFY_CONFLICT:</p>

<pre><code>printf("conflict\n");
break;
</code></pre>

<p>  case GIT_CHECKOUT_NOTIFY_DIRTY:</p>

<pre><code>printf("dirty\n");
break;
</code></pre>

<p>  case GIT_CHECKOUT_NOTIFY_UPDATED:</p>

<pre><code>printf("updated\n");
break;
</code></pre>

<p>  case GIT_CHECKOUT_NOTIFY_UNTRACKED:</p>

<pre><code>printf("untracked\n");
break;
</code></pre>

<p>  case GIT_CHECKOUT_NOTIFY_IGNORED:</p>

<pre><code>printf("ignored\n");
break;
</code></pre>

<p>  default:
  break;
  }</p>

<p>  return 0;
}</p>

<p>// ...
git_checkout_opts opts = GIT_CHECKOUT_OPTS_INIT;
opts.checkout_strategy = GIT_CHECKOUT_SAFE;
opts.notify_flags =
  GIT_CHECKOUT_NOTIFY_CONFLICT |
  GIT_CHECKOUT_NOTIFY_DIRTY |
  GIT_CHECKOUT_NOTIFY_UPDATED |
  GIT_CHECKOUT_NOTIFY_UNTRACKED |
  GIT_CHECKOUT_NOTIFY_IGNORED;
opts.notify_cb = checkout_notify_cb;
git_checkout_head(repo, &amp;opts);
```</p>

<p>Here's some example output.
I've created the <code>.gitignore</code> file so that <code>foo</code> will be ignored, and changed the contents of <code>master.txt</code>.</p>

<p><code>text
path '.gitignore' - untracked
path 'a/a1.txt' - dirty
path 'foo' - ignored
checkout:   0% - (null)
</code></p>

<p>I've left the progress callback as-is, so you can see how these two features interact -- notifications happen as checkout is <em>determining what to do</em>, and progress callbacks happen as checkout is <em>doing the things</em>.</p>

<p>That's when the checkout strategy is set to <code>GIT_CHECKOUT_SAFE_CREATE</code>.
Watch what happens when I change it to this:</p>

<p><code>c
opts.checkout_strategy =
  GIT_CHECKOUT_FORCE |
  GIT_CHECKOUT_REMOVE_UNTRACKED;
</code></p>

<p><code>text
path '.gitignore' - untracked
path 'a/a1.txt' - dirty
path 'a/a1.txt' - updated
path 'foo' - ignored
checkout:   0% - (null)
checkout:  50% - .gitignore
checkout: 100% - a/a1.txt
</code></p>

<p>You can see that <code>a/a1.txt</code> was updated in the index, and if we had specified a progress callback, you'd see it being written in the working directory.</p>

<p>We also asked checkout to remove untracked files (but not ignored ones), so it deleted the <code>.gitignore</code> file, leaving <code>foo</code> as untracked instead of ignored.
If we run it again:</p>

<p>```text
path 'foo' - untracked
checkout:   0% - (null)
checkout: 100% - foo</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>... it removes the <code>foo</code> file as well.</p>

<p>One other capability that the notification callback gives you is <em>the ability to cancel the checkout</em> before any changes have been written to disk.
Just return something other than <code>0</code>, and the process will simply be aborted.</p>

<h2>One file at a time</h2>

<p>What if you don't want to check out the entire working directory?
What if you just want to discard the changes made to one file?
The options structure has a field for you -- it's named <code>paths</code>, and it's of type <code>git_strarray</code>.</p>

<p>Despite the name, it's actually an array of fnmatch-patterns, like <code>"foo/*"</code> -- the same format as you'd use in a <code>.gitignore</code> file.
Continuing our earlier example, if I wanted to limit the files checkout is looking at to just the files in the <code>a</code> directory, I could do this:</p>

<p><code>c
char *paths[] = { "a/*" };
opts.paths.strings = paths;
opts.paths.count = 1;
</code></p>

<p>And the output would look something like this:</p>

<p><code>text
path 'a/a1.txt' - dirty
path 'a/a1.txt' - updated
checkout:   0% - (null)
checkout: 100% - a/a1.txt
</code></p>

<p>Note there's no mention of <code>.gitignore</code> or <code>foo</code>; they're filtered out by path matching before any of the diff logic is even applied.</p>

<h2>Not <code>HEAD</code></h2>

<p>All of the examples we've seen so far use <code>git_checkout_head</code>.
What if you want to pull out content that isn't from <code>HEAD</code>?
We saw in the beginning that you can easily pull content out of the index by doing this:</p>

<p><code>c
git_checkout_index(repo, NULL, &amp;opts);
</code></p>

<p>This gets content from the index and writes it to the working directory.
It's similar to doing <code>git checkout [file]</code> without specifying a branch or revision.
That <code>NULL</code> parameter could also refer to a separate index, which is a bit beyond the scope of this post.</p>

<p>You can also pull content from elsewhere in the history.
For instance, to replicate something like <code>git checkout HEAD~~ master.txt</code>, you could do this:</p>

<p>```c
char *paths[] = {"master.txt"};
opts.paths.strings = paths;
opts.paths.count = 1;</p>

<p>// Get "HEAD<del>"
git_commit <em>commit;
git_revparse_single((git_object</em>)&amp;commit, repo, "HEAD</del>");</p>

<p>// Do the checkout
git_checkout_tree(repo, commit, &amp;opts);</p>

<p>// Clean up
git_commit_free(commit);
```</p>

<h2>That's about it</h2>

<p><strong>NOTE: You should do error checking.</strong>
You should also check out the documentations comments in the <a href="https://github.com/libgit2/libgit2/blob/HEAD/include/git2/checkout.h#files"><code>git2/checkout.h</code></a> header -- they're really well-written, and they cover more than what I've got here.</p>

<p>## What now?

I dunno.
What are you trying to do?
You could always check out my [other libgit2 posts](/blog/categories/libgit2/) for some ideas.
Or look for help [everywhere else](https://www.google.com/search?q=how%20do%20I%20use%20libgit2%20to).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[libgit2: The Repository]]></title>
    <link href="http://ben.github.com/2013/03/05/libgit2-the-repository/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-05T12:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://ben.github.com/2013/03/05/libgit2-the-repository</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://libgit2.github.com/">libgit2</a>, the <code>git_repository</code> object is the gateway to getting interesting stuff out of git.
There are several ways to get your hands on one.</p>

<h2>Clone</h2>

<p>If your repository exists on a remote but not on the local machine, you can get it using <a href="http://libgit2.github.com/libgit2/#HEAD/group/repository/git_clone"><code>git_clone</code></a>, and once it's done with all the network stuff, it spits out a repository object.
Check out <a href="/2013/02/01/stupid-libgit2-tricks-cloning/">my post on cloning</a> for more on that.</p>

<h2>Discover</h2>

<p>If you know a particular directory is a git repository, you can just hand the path to <a href="http://libgit2.github.com/libgit2/#HEAD/group/repository/git_repository_open"><code>git_repository_open</code></a>.
The path can be to a bare repository, a <code>.git</code> folder, or a working directory.</p>

<p><code>c
git_repository *repo;
int error = git_repository_open(
  &amp;repo,
  "/path/to/repository/on/disk");
</code></p>

<p>In classic C fashion, libgit2 APIs generally return 0 on success, and a negative error code on failure.
Occasionally the API documentation will mention the specific error codes that will come back, but you can always check the <a href="https://github.com/libgit2/libgit2/blob/HEAD/include/git2/errors.h#files">error header</a> for the values.</p>

<p>If all you have is a path that you <em>think</em> is controlled by git, you can let libgit2 walk the directory structure to find it's owning repository (if there is one).
This approach works well if your application is dealing primarily with documents, like a text editor.</p>

<p><code>c
char path[1024];
if (0 == git_repository_discover(
  path, 1024,                       // buffer &amp; size
  "/path/to/a/controlled/file.md",  // where to start
  true,                             // across filesystems?
  "/path"))                         // where to stop
{
  git_repository *repo;
  error = git_repository_open(&amp;repo, path);
}
</code></p>

<h2>Initialize</h2>

<p>If you want to create a new repository, <a href="http://libgit2.github.com/libgit2/#HEAD/group/repository/git_repository_init"><code>git_repository_init</code></a> is the call for you.</p>

<p><code>c
git_repository *repo;
int error = git_repository_init(
  &amp;repo,                // output
  "path/to/new/repo",   // path
  false);               // bare?
</code></p>

<p>This is kind of like running <code>git init</code> from the command line.
If you need more control, you'll use <a href="http://libgit2.github.com/libgit2/#HEAD/group/repository/git_repository_init_ext"><code>git_repository_init_ext</code></a>:</p>

<p><code>c
git_repository *repo;
git_repository_init_options options =
  GIT_REPOSITORY_INIT_OPTIONS_INIT;
// ... (configure options)
int error = git_repository_init_ext(
  &amp;repo,                // output
  "/path/to/new/repo",  // path
  &amp;options);            // options
</code></p>

<p>The signature itself looks similar to the simpler version, but that options structure exposes <strong>lots</strong> of behavior.
Things like:</p>

<ul>
<li>separating your <code>.git</code> directory from the workdir</li>
<li>adding a description or using a template</li>
<li>setting the initial branch name</li>
</ul>


<p>Unfortunately, as of this writing the documentation parser doesn't output structure-field comment-docs, but the <a href="https://github.com/libgit2/libgit2/blob/HEAD/include/git2/repository.h#files">header</a> is pretty helpful.</p>

<p>## What now?

I dunno.
What are you trying to do?
You could always check out my [other libgit2 posts](/blog/categories/libgit2/) for some ideas.
Or look for help [everywhere else](https://www.google.com/search?q=how%20do%20I%20use%20libgit2%20to).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[libgit2: Cloning]]></title>
    <link href="http://ben.github.com/2013/02/01/stupid-libgit2-tricks-cloning/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-01T10:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://ben.github.com/2013/02/01/stupid-libgit2-tricks-cloning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://libgit2.github.com">Libgit2</a> aims to make it easy to do interesting things
with git.  What's the first thing you always do when learning git?  That's
right, you clone something from GitHub.  Let's get started, shall we? Let's get
some of the boilerplate out of the way:</p>

<p>```c</p>

<h1>include "git2.h"</h1>

<h1>include &lt;stdio.h></h1>

<p>int main(int argc, char **argv)
{</p>

<pre><code>const char *url, *path;

if (argc &lt; 3) {
    printf("USAGE: clone &lt;url&gt; &lt;path&gt;\n");
    return -1;
}

url = argv[1];
path = argv[2];
return do_clone(url, path);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>What does the do_clone method look like?  Let's start simple:</p>

<p>```c
static int do_clone(const char <em>url, const char </em>path)
{</p>

<pre><code>git_repository *repo = NULL;
int ret = git_clone(&amp;repo, url, path, NULL);
git_repository_free(repo);
return ret;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p><code>git_clone</code> takes some information, and fills in a pointer for us with
a <code>git_repository</code> object we can use to do <em>all manner of unholy things</em>.  For
now, let's ignore the repository itself, except to be good citizens and release
the memory associated with it.</p>

<p>That <code>NULL</code> parameter?  That's for a <code>git_clone_options</code> structure, which
defaults to some sensible stuff.  The way our code is written right now, these
two commands will have the same results:</p>

<p><code>sh
./clone http://github.com/libgit2/libgit2 ./libgit2
git clone http://github.com/libgit2/libgit2
</code></p>

<p>... except that <code>git</code> tells you what it's doing.  Let's fix that.</p>

<p>One of the things you can do with <code>git_clone_options</code> is have libgit2 call
a function when there is progress to report.  A typical callback looks like
this:</p>

<p>```c
static void fetch_progress(</p>

<pre><code>    const git_transfer_progress *stats,
    void *payload)
</code></pre>

<p>{</p>

<pre><code>int fetch_percent =
    (100 * stats-&gt;received_objects) /
    stats-&gt;total_objects;
int index_percent =
    (100 * stats-&gt;indexed_objects) /
    stats-&gt;total_objects;
int kbytes = stats-&gt;received_bytes / 1024;

printf("network %3d%% (%4d kb, %5d/%5d)  /"
        "  index %3d%% (%5d/%5d)\n",
        fetch_percent, kbytes,
        stats-&gt;received_objects, stats-&gt;total_objects,
        index_percent,
        stats-&gt;indexed_objects, stats-&gt;total_objects);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>That <code>stats</code> object gives you lots of useful stuff:</p>

<ul>
<li>The number of objects transferred over the network</li>
<li>The number of objects that the indexer has processed</li>
<li>The total number of objects expected</li>
<li>The number of bytes transferred</li>
</ul>


<p>So let's rewrite our <code>do_clone</code> function to plug that in:</p>

<p>```c
static int do_clone(const char <em>url, const char </em>path)
{</p>

<pre><code>git_repository *repo = NULL;
git_clone_options opts = GIT_CLONE_OPTIONS_INIT;
int ret;

opts.fetch_progress_cb = fetch_progress;
ret = git_clone(&amp;repo, url, path, &amp;opts);
git_repository_free(repo);
return ret;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>If you run this now, the program will tell you what it's doing!  You can watch
the network transfer happening, and notice that the indexer is doing its job
<em>at the same time</em>.</p>

<p><code>text
[...]
network  73% (   7 kb,    51/   69)  /  index  71% (   49/   69)
network  75% (   7 kb,    52/   69)  /  index  72% (   50/   69)
network  76% (   7 kb,    53/   69)  /  index  73% (   51/   69)
network  78% (   7 kb,    54/   69)  /  index  75% (   52/   69)
[...]
</code></p>

<p>If you try this with a large repository, you'll notice a significant pause at
the end.  All the data has been moved, what's going on?  It turns out that
doing a checkout can take a non-trivial amount of time.  It also turns out that
libgit2 will let you report that progress as well!</p>

<p>But that's part of checkout, which warrants its own blog post.  In the
meantime, check out the <a href="https://github.com/libgit2/libgit2/blob/development/include/git2/clone.h">clone
header</a>
to see what <code>git_clone</code> can do.  If you want to, you could even use the <a href="https://gist.github.com/4693571">code
from this post</a> as a starting point for your
own experiments.</p>

<p>## What now?

I dunno.
What are you trying to do?
You could always check out my [other libgit2 posts](/blog/categories/libgit2/) for some ideas.
Or look for help [everywhere else](https://www.google.com/search?q=how%20do%20I%20use%20libgit2%20to).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
